Guide to the Time Inc. Fortune Editorial Records 1951-2013 MS 3009-RG 8
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Fortune Editorial Records
1951-2013
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 8
21.75 Linear feet in 23 record cartons
The Fortune Editorial Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the editorial side of the magazine, not the publishing or business side. Staff represented in this record group include managing editor Robert Lubar, managing editor Louis Banks, managing editor Duncan Nortan-Taylor, managing editor Andrew Serwer, staff writer Charles Burck, and staff writer Rush Loving Jr. Also included are materials from the Art Department on planning and creating issues in 1982 and files on staff, freelance writers, and other contributors to Fortune.
Arrangement
This record group is arranged into four series:
Series I. Managing Editor Files
Series II. Staff Writer Files
Series III. Art Department Files
Series IV. Personnel and Contributors Files
Historical Note
For the majority of Time Inc.'s existence, the company maintained a strict separation of editorial from the publishing and business side of each magazine, colloquially called the separation of "church" (editorial) and "state" (publishing). Publishing and Business Management includes the publisher, general manager, business manager, advertising sales, marketing services, letters, circulation, and public relations. The editorial side reported up to the editor-in-chief and the publishing/business side reported up to the corporate business executive which was the president prior to 1960 and the chief executive officer after. Henry Luce structured Time Inc. this way so that the business side could not (in theory) influence the editorial content of the publications. For example, the advertising sales people could not interfere with a magazine's decision to run an article on the dangers of cigarette smoking, even though it might mean losing millions of dollars in tobacco ads.
In September 1928, Time Inc. cofounder Henry Luce presented cofounder Briton Hadden with an idea for a new magazine. Luce wanted to create a magazine that would cater to the men who ran businesses in the United States. This magazine would offer business men a sophisticated perspective on industrial business and its role in society. To cater to this clientele, the magazine would feature richly illustrated pages as well as high quality editorial content. Hadden was not convinced that Luce's idea would work but agreed to let Parker Lloyd-Smith, a business writer at Time, and some researchers explore Luce's idea. In February 1929, not long after Hadden's sudden death, Luce went to the board of Time Inc. with his idea and proposed the launch of Fortune. At this meeting, Luce presented the board with a description of the magazine's appearance and an outline of its contents. This outline included samples of some articles that had already been written as well as illustrations. A few months after Fortune was proposed, the board agreed to proceed with the idea and the first issue of the magazine was released in February 1930.
Much like with Time, Luce named himself Fortune's editor. One of the first editorial decisions that Luce made was about how financial news would be presented. In other magazines and newspapers with similar content, facts and statistics were present in a straightforward fashion with no embellishment. To change this, Luce decided to hire literary talent instead of business experts or economists. Some of the talent that was recruited overs the years to work on Fortune included James Agee, John Kenneth Galbraith, Ernest Hemingway, Alfred Kazin, Dwight Macdonald, Archibald MacLeish, and Miné Okubo. Because Fortune was taking a more literary approach to its content, there were human interest stories alongside in-depth articles about major businesses and industries. In addition to the change in editorial material, Fortune also changed the approach to the advertisements and images used in the magazine. Instead of the standard black and white images, there was an emphasis on colorful advertisements and striking art, illustrations, and photographs. To make the imagery in the magazine stand out, Fortune recruited well-known artists and photographers. Included among those who have worked for Fortune over the years are Ansel Adams, Constantin Alajálov, John Atherton, Herbert Bayer, Lester Beal, Thomas Benrimo, Joseph Binder, Margaret Bourke-White, A.M. Cassandre, Thomas Maitland Cleland, Miguel Covarrubias, Walker Evans, George Gusti, Fernand Léger, Fred Ludekens, Erik Nitsche, Antonio Petruccelli, Diego Rivera, Ben Shahn, and Charles Sheeler. To receive a copy of this newly released magazine, members of the public needed to become subscribers. Despite there being no focus groups or trial issues to introduce buyers to the product, there were 30,000 subscribers at the time of the magazine's release. The initial copies cost $1 each or $10 for a yearly subscription. At the time, this was a steep price and was meant to act as a barrier so that only the most passionate and well off customers could afford to read it.
Fortune was well received by critics and industry professionals alike. By the end of 1930 and the release of the first eleven issues, the magazine's circulation had increased by 10,000 and was turning a profit for Time Inc. Despite the strong start, Fortune suffered difficulties after the end of World War II and was beginning to become unprofitable. At the same time that the magazine was experiencing financial trouble, members of Fortune's board of editors started to believe that the magazine was suffering from problems on the editorial side as well. Members of the board of editors suggested that the magazine had a lack of cohesion and no new ideas. Upon hearing these doubts, Luce decided to make some changes to the magazine and change its focus. The magazine would provide guidance to those interested in America's political economy. The changes upset the magazine's editors and writers, but renewed the interest of businessmen and helped increase the magazine's circulation.
Despite this somewhat tumultuous beginning, Fortune is still in print as of 2018. Over time the magazine has changed its publication schedule. Originally a monthly publications, the magazine became a bi-weekly publication in 1978 but switched to tri-weekly publication in 2009. While the magazine is primarily published in the United States, the magazine has had international editions as well. Many of these editions are no longer in print. These changes in Fortune's publication schedule coincided with an increase in demand for the magazine. With the growth of the magazine's popularity with the general public, editors and writers from Fortune began to make appearances on radio and television shows to share information found in the latest articles. The magazine also hosted its own short-lived television show Fortune Week which was on CNBC from 1993 to 1994.
Citations:
"About Us: Our History, Our Mission, Our Editorial Standards, and Who We Are." Fortune. July 20, 2018. Accessed November 08, 2018. http://fortune.com/about-us/.
"Background Information - Fortune Magazine in the 1930s." Fortune in the 1930s. Accessed November 08, 2018. http://xroads.virginia.edu/~1930s/print/fortune/background.html.
Brooks, Tim, and Earle Marsh. The Complete Directory to Prime Time Network and Cable TV Shows (1946-present). New York: Ballantine, 2000. Accessed January 07, 2019.
Elson, Robert T. Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise: 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum, 1968.
Elson, Robert T. The World of Time Inc: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise: 1941-1960. Edited by Duncan Norton-Taylor. New York: Atheneum, 1973.
Gibbs, Wolcott. "Time... Fortune... Life... Luce." The New Yorker. June 20, 2017. Accessed November 08, 2018. https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/1936/11/28/time-fortune-life-luce.4
Hooper, Bill. Email to Holly Deakyne, 10 June 2016.
Okrent, Daniel. "How the World Really Works." Fortune. September 19, 2005. Accessed November 08, 2018. http://archive.fortune.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2005/09/19/8272901/index.htm
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include contracts and consent forms. Restricted boxes include 2215 and R42. Unreformatted audiovisual and digital material in the collection is not accessible. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Information about the history of Fortune and additional records from the editorial offices can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39). Records from the publishing and business offices are in the Time Inc. Fortune Publishing and Business Records (MS 3009-RG 25).
Scope and Contents
The Fortune Editorial Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the editorial side of the magazine. There are no materials from the publishing or business side of the operation.
Staff represented in this record group include managing editor Robert Lubar, managing editor Louis Banks, managing editor Duncan Nortan-Taylor, managing editor Andrew Serwer, staff writer Charles Burck, and staff writer Rush Loving Jr. Additionally, there are departmental files from the Art Department and Personnel. Included in this record group are clippings, correspondence, memoranda, notes, transcripts, drafts, field reports, industry reports, newspapers, press releases, press kits, presentations, and audio cassettes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. 2015.
Audiotapes; Clippings (information artifacts); Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Correspondence.; Dispatches; Drafts (documents); Editors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Interviews.; Journalists -- United States.; Notes (documents); Organization files.; Press releases.; Press kits.; Reporters and reporting -- United States.; Speeches (documents); Banks, Louis, 1916-1993; Burck, Charles; Loving, Rush; Lubar, Robert, -1995; Norton-Taylor, Duncan; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History
- Series I.A. Managing Editor Louis Banks Correspondence, 1968-1970; 0.25 Linear feet in 4 folders
  Biographical / Historical
  Louis Banks started at Time Inc. in 1945 as a news correspondent in Los Angeles. He served as managing editor of Fortune from 1965 to 1970 with a brief leave of absence in 1969 for a fellowship at Harvard University. He returned to Time Inc. in 1970 as a corporate editorial director. By 1974, he was on the board of Time Inc. and held this position through 1987.
  Citations:
  "Louis Banks, 77, Dies; An Editor for Time Inc." The New York Times. November 11, 1993. Accessed August 1, 2019. https://www.nytimes.com/1993/11/11/obituaries/louis-banks-77-dies-an-editor-for-time-inc.html
  Personnel and Organization: Department Head Lists. Time Inc. Reference Files (MS 3009-RG 3), The New-York Historical Society.
  Scope and Contents
  Managing Editor Louis Bank's correspondence files contain correspondence that Banks sent and received during his time as Fortune managing editor. Records primarily include exchanges with heads of companies regarding events attended, follow up to visits or interviews, article ideas, and sometimes include speech transcripts and copies of articles to read. One item of interest is a 1968 letter from the Museum of Modern Art thanking him for the Time Inc. gift of over 1000 photographs from the Fortune and Architectural Forum files to the Department of Architecture and Design.
  Arrangement
  Organized chronologically based on the original order.
  - Corrrespondence, 1968 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 4)
- Series I.B. Managing Editor Robert Lubar Correspondence, 1969-1977; 1.5 Linear feet in 3 record cartons
  Biographical Note
  Robert "Bob" Lubar began his career with Time Inc. in 1946 as a writer for Time in Manhattan. During his tenure with Time, Lubar held posts in London, New Delhi, Bonn, and Mexico City. After 12 years with Time, in 1958, Lubar was moved to Fortune where he was promoted to the position of associate editor.
  Lubar remained an associate editor for six years before becoming assistant managing editor in 1964. While his predecessor Managing Editor Louis Banks was on leave as a fellow at Harvard in 1969, Lubar filled in as acting managing editor. In early 1970, Lubar was signing off as an executive editor. In later 1970, he took over from Banks as managing editor of Fortune.
  During the ten years that Lubar was managing editor, he oversaw the transition of the magazine to a smaller format and the magazine's move from a monthly to bi-weekly publication. After leaving his position as managing editor, Lubar remained with Fortune as a chief of research until he retired in 1985.
  "Robert Lubar, 74, Writer and Editor." The New York Times. April 9, 1995. Accessed December 3, 2018. https://www.nytimes.com/1995/04/09/obituaries/robert-lubar-74-writer-and-editor.html.
  Managing Editor Robert Lubar's correspondence files cover the period of 1969 to 1977 and contain correspondence that Lubar sent and received during his time as assistant managing editor, acting managing editor, executive editor, and managing editor of Fortune. Records include responses to company executive readers, responses regarding article errors, and arrangements with guest writers. The topics covered in the correspondence include discussion of editorials, the relationship between government and businesses, requests for meetings and speakers, requests for assistance with research projects, restaurant and research recommendations, and meeting and conference agenda. Correspondence files from 1971 were not found while processing the series although one exchange with Roy Hurley was found later among unrelated material.
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 5-7)
  - Cables, 1970 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 9-11)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 12a)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 12b)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 13-17)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 18-21)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Offsite-box 3301, Folder 22-24)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Offsite-box 2885, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence [RESTRICTED], 1976 (Offsite-box R42)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Offsite-box 2885, Folder 3-6)
- Series I.C. Managing Editor Andrew Serwer Desk Objects, circa 1980-2013; 3 Linear feet in 3 record cartons
  Andrew "Andy" Serwer Desk Objects contains the items that were cleared from his desk when he left Fortune in 2014 after serving as the managing editor from 2006 to 2014. Items include awards received by Fortune, awards received by Serwer as a representative of Time Inc., mementos of Time Inc. on the stock market, gifts from a business trip to China, issues of Fortune signed by major company executives, and other desk realia.
  The objects are in no order.
  - Desk Items, 1992-2012 (Offsite-box 3298)
    Contains items from Serwer's 2011 business trip to China including framed photographs and gifts received from hosts including glass fish; 1992 Fortune/Ford Motor Company: Top Ten Biggest Mistakes Wooden item; Joseph Pulitzer Quote Block; 2011 NASDAQ framed photograph; National Association of Multicultural Media Executives 2008 Award of Valor; NYSE Closing Bell Mementoes from 2011 and 2012; NYSE NYX Listed Bell; 1992 Wellfleet Communications plastic desk item. Also included is a framed Pope's Mitre Fragment with a note on the back that states the Pope's Mitre resided in the the office of the Editor-in-Chief symbolizing the belief in editorial independence, truth and integrity.
  - Desk Items, 2008-2011 (Offsite-box 3299)
    Contains 2008 Beijing Olympics commemorative medal; items from Serwer's 2011 business trip to China including framed photographs and gifts received from hosts including glass fish; business card name plate; 2008 Folio Magazine Eddie Award; small glass globe; two NASDAQ Opening Bell Mementos; and a cloth banner for Time.
  - Desk Items, circa 1980-2013 (Offsite-box 3300)
    Contains 2009 Folio Magazine Eddie Award; 1996 hardcover issue of Fortune; 2012 and 2013 issues of Fortune signed by major company executives; 2013 National Magazine Finalist Award; and 1978 hardcover first issue of The New Fortune. Also included is Serwer's Teletalk intercom.
- Series I.D. Managing Editor Planning Committee Files, 1966-1972; 1 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
  The Managing Editor Planning Committee files cover the period of 1966 to 1972 and includes materials collected by several managing editors of Fortune including Duncan Norton-Taylor, Robert Lubar, and Louis Banks. The materials were used while planning magazine issues of Fortune. Records include drafts of articles, raw field reports from reporters, and memoranda and internal correspondence discussing story ideas, articles published in other magazines and papers, and reporter research findings.
  Organized chronologically.
  - 1967 Planning Committee, 1966-1967, undated (Offsite-box 2885, Folder 7-8)
  - 1968 Planning Committee, 1968, undated (Offsite-box 2885, Folder 9-11)
  - 1969 Planning Committee, 1969, undated (Offsite-box 2885, Folder 12-15)
  - 1970 Planning Committee, 1970, undated (Offsite-box 2885, Folder 16-19)
  - 1971 Planning Committee, 1970-1972, undated (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 1-4)
- Series I.E. Managing Editor Subject Files, 1959-1979; 2 Linear feet in 3 record cartons
  The Managing Editor Subject files include materials from 1959 to 1979 and were collected by several managing editors at Fortune including Duncan Norton-Taylor, Robert Lubar, and Louis Banks. Records focus on a proposed transition to publishing Fortune biweekly; the establishment of President, the Japanese version of Fortune; the planning of special issues of Fortune; seminars hosted by Fortune; and include correspondence with story ideas and comments on articles. Also included are reports on events, schedules, clippings, and correspondence discussing meetings, plans for magazine issues, and responses to articles. The President files include negotitions on which Fortune articles to reprint, a letter detailing the structure and content of the first issue, and a report from a President staff member regarding what she learned during her visit to observe the editorial operations of Fortune.
  Organized alphabetically.
  - Ackerman, Edward A., circa 1972 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 1)
  - Alfred Politz Research: Report on Executive Attitudes on Mergers, 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 2)
  - American Society of Magazine Editors, 1975 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 3)
  - Biweekly Fortune, 1975-1977 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 4-6)
  - Copy Processing, 1972 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 7)
  - Economic Series in 1974, 1973 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 8)
  - Editorial Development Directive for Fortune, undated (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 5)
  - Experimental Projects: Biweekly Fortune, 1967 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 9)
  - Glen Cove Economists Dinner: Dr. Mesthene Group, 1971 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 10)
  - Goodrich, 1969, undated (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 6)
  - Langenhove, Fernand van, 1960 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 11)
  - Legal, 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 12-13)
  - Memoranda, 1975 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 14)
  - Moonshot: Apollo 17, 1972 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 15)
  - Penn Central: Article Dispute, 1970 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 16)
  - Political Research Center Investment, 1974? (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 17)
  - President Magazine, 1962-1968 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 18-20)
  - Seminar: Chicago: 1971 May 24-25 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 7)
  - South African Supplement, 1971 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 8)
  - Special Issue: 1967 Sept. 15 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 9)
  - Special Issue: 1968 Sept. 15 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 10)
  - Special Issue: 500 Issue: 1968 June 15 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 11)
  - Special Issue: 500-50: 1966 mid-July - 1967 June 15, 1966-1967, undated (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 12)
  - Special Issue: American Crisis, 1970 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 21)
  - Special Issue: Business and Environment: 1970 Feb., 1969 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 13)
  - Special Issue: Innovation Industry, 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 14)
  - Special Issue: Latin America: 1962 Feb., 1961, undated (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 15)
  - Special Issue: "Negro" [African American]: Cities: 1968 Jan., 1967-1968, undated (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 16)
  - Special Issue: New York: 1960 Feb., 1959-1960, undated (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 17-18)
  - Special Issue: Space: 1962 June, 1962, undated (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 19)
  - Special Issue: Transportation, 1971 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 22)
  - Special Issue: Youth, 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 20-21)
  - Staff Correspondence and Memoranda, 1964-1977 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 23)
  - Staff Salaries, 1968? (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 24)
  - Stonehenge, 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 22-24)
  - Story Comment, 1972-1974 (Offsite-box 2886, Folder 25-28)
  - Story Comment, 1975-1979 (Offsite-box 2887, Folder 1-10)
  - Story Suggestion, 1978 (Offsite-box 2887, Folder 11)
  - Tapes, circa 1966 (Offsite-box 3302, Folder 25)
    Includes audiovisual material with dictation from Louis Banks:
    2 audio belts (Magnabelt).
- Series II.A. Staff Writer Charles Burck Files, 1951-1985; 7.25 Linear feet in 10 record cartons
  Charles Burck was a writer at Fortune from 1965 through 1994.
  The Staff Writer Charles Burck files are records that Burck created or collected while researching and writing articles. The majority of materials focus on the articles Burck wrote about the automobile industry and youth and left wing activist movements. Included in this series are independent/underground newspapers, United States government reports on the auto industry, trends charts, notes on production costs, reports comparing United States and Japanese auto industries, copies of presentation slides, notes on prices, drafts, raw reports, lists of contacts, press releases, clippings, bumper stickers, political flyers, booklets and pamphlets about political groups and activities, audio cassettes, drafts of articles, transcripts of speeches and presentations, and correspondence with information for Burck's stories or comments on his published articles. Included among the independent newspapers that Burck collected were the San Francisco Express Times, Rat, The Free You, Kaleidoscope, the Berkeley Barb, the East Village Other, Natural Weapon, Blimp Works, the Realist, Fire Next Time, Orpheus, Zodiac Mind Warp, Bloom, Open City Press, Peninsula Observer, Yellow Dog, and The Movement as well as other titles.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Auto Industry: Air Standards, 1970-1979, 1985, undated (Offsite-box 2891, Folder 13)
  - Auto Industry: Auto Costs: Notes, 1979-1982, undated (Offsite-box 2891, Folder 14-17)
  - Auto Industry: Auto Costs: Reports, Studies, Statistics, 1981, undated (Offsite-box 2891, Folder 18-19)
  - Auto Industry: Comeback Decade, 1980, undated (Offsite-box 2891, Folder 20)
  - Auto Industry: Correspondence: Stern/Cordtz: 1974 July (Offsite-box 2891, Folder 21)
  - Auto Industry: Earlier Stories and Notes, 1977, undated (Offsite-box 2892, Folder 1)